{"tossups": [{"question": "This city is home to a Daniel Johnston mural depicting a frog named Jeremiah saying, \"Hi, How Are You?\" This city is also home to bronze sculptures of musicians Willie Nelson and Stevie Ray Vaughan. A university tower in this city was the staging ground of a mass murder carried out by Charles Whitman. Home to the world's largest urban bat colony, this city was originally founded in 1839 and named Waterloo, though it soon changed its name to recognize a state hero. Sitting on the banks of Lady Bird Lake, for ten points, name this capital of Texas.", "answer": "<b><u>Austin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This structure uses two standards, A and B, for offsets. Coel Hen [[COIL HEN]], the legendary father of Saint Helena, used some buildings on this structure. John Clayton helped preserve this structure which parallels the Stanegate Road. A path following this structure passes a fort at Housesteads. This structure included an earthwork called the <em>Vallum</em>, and it was guarded by Milecastles. Located on the border of the Roman Empire and similar to the Antonine, for ten points, what is this fortification across Scotland?", "answer": "<b><u>Hadrian's Wall</u></b> (prompt on \"Roman Wall\"; accept <b><u>Picts' Wall</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In support of the use of this resource, William H. Harvey published the pamphlet <em>Coin's Financial School</em> which claimed the ills of a late-19th century depression could have been avoided by utilizing this resource. The Comstock Lode outside Virginia City, Nevada, was rich in this resource. William Jennings Bryan championed the cause of bimetallism, which aimed to fix currency to gold and this other resource. For ten points, name this shiny white metal often used in coinage.", "answer": "<b><u>Silver</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ag</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After the release of this film, Canada\u2019s Fairview Lawn Cemetery was overrun with visitors, particularly around the grave of Joseph Dawson. Six weeks after this movie\u2019s release, seven percent of American teenage girls had seen it twice, and it made more money in its eleventh week in theaters than in its first. For ten points, name this 1997 James Cameron-directed movie, the first to ever gross more than a billion dollars, named for the title doomed ocean liner.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Titanic</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A vigilante group that operated in the southwest of this state, named the Bald Knobbers, rooted out outlaws with Confederate sympathies. Future outlaw Jesse James, a native of this state, took part in the sacking of neighboring Kansas's city of Lawrence. A \"Compromise\" named for this state led to its 1820 admittance into the Union along with the state of Maine. For ten points, name this state which stayed in the Union, the site of the so-called \u201cSt. Louis Massacre.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Missouri</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In riots named for this illness, the urban poor and peasants alike gathered in Sennaya Square, St. Petersburg to demonstrate against the Russian Empire. John Snow curtailed an outbreak of this disease after tracking the source to a water pump in Broad Street, London. Gabriel Garcia Marquez set a novel about Florentino\u2019s undying love for Fermina within the backdrop of an epidemic of this disease. For ten points, name this bacterial infection which is caused by contamination of a water source and results in massive dehydration in its victims.", "answer": "<b><u>Cholera</u></b> (accept Asiatic <b><u>cholera</u></b>; accept Epidemic <b><u>cholera</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "In the Peloponnese, this god's cult depicted him as a singular horse. Along with Apollo, this god watched over Greek colonists during their travels. This god's signature weapon was created by the Telchines [[TEL-kines]], and, according to legend, this husband of Amphitrite [[am-fih-TRY-tee]] offered a salt water spring in an attempt to become the patron god of Athens. This god was worshipped in his \"earth shaker\" form due to his ability to cause earthquakes by striking the ground with his trident. For ten points, name this Greek god of the ocean.", "answer": "<b><u>Poseidon</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \"Neptune\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "At the beginning of this uprising, Robert Bealknap attempted mass arrests of its participants. A former employee of Geoffrey Chaucer, William Walworth, killed the leader of this revolt at the Battle of Smithfield. During this revolt, leaders Jack Straw and Wat Tyler planned to kill the sitting king, Richard II, in part due to high taxes which were levied on the underclass during the Hundred Years\u2019 War. For ten points, name this 14th century English revolt, named for the agrarian class who rose up against the nobility.", "answer": "<b><u>Peasants\u2019</u></b> Revolt (accept <b><u>Wat Tyler</u></b>\u2019s Revolt before mentioned; accept <b><u>Great</u></b> <b><u>Rising</u></b>; accept \"Rebellion\" or \"Uprising\" in place of \"Revolt\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Major indigenous ethnic groups from this island include the Atayal and the Kanakanavu. This island is widely believed to be the origin of the Austronesian language family. This island is home to the former Dutch East India Company-owned Fort Zealandia, and this island's tallest building is a 101-story skyscraper modelled after a shoot of bamboo. After losing a civil war, the Kuomintang party fled to this island, which was formerly known as Formosa. For ten points, name this East Asian island nation whose largest city is Taipei.", "answer": "<b><u>Taiwan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Republic of China</u></b>; accept <b><u>ROC</u></b>; accept <b><u>Formosa</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "George McClellan fought a short engagement at this site during the Peninsular Campaign, forcing John MacGruder to retreat to Williamsburg. An American force was bolstered by the Exp\u00e9dition Particuli\u00e8re, led by the Comte de Rochambeau [[roh-sham-BOH]], in a siege at this site. That battle at this site led to the surrender of General Cornwallis, who presented his sword to General Washington through his aide-de-camp. For ten points, give this site of the final battle of the American Revolution.", "answer": "<b><u>Yorktown</u></b>, Virginia", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country was unified when it joined with Eastern Rumelia. In the Second Balkan War, five countries teamed up to beat this nation causing a vengeful attitude which drove this country to join the Central Powers. In 1919, this country lost Thrace and Dobruja via the Treaty of Neuilly-sur-Seine [[nwee-LEE-suhr-SEN]]. The establishment of an autonomous principality that corresponds to this country was guaranteed by Russia at the Treaty of San Stefano. For ten points, name this country with capital at Sofia.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Bulgaria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "George Reisner [[RYE-snur]] abandoned excavation of these places due to flooding which collapsed tunnels and killed his crew. Giuseppe Ferlini destroyed several of these places while searching for treasure in Mero\u00eb [[MEH-row-ee]]. According to legend, one of the first examples of these places was designed by Imhotep for Djoser [[JOH-ser]]. The largest example of these places was built for Khufu. For ten points, name these massive tombs, whose \"Great\" examples are located in Giza, Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Pyramid</u></b> (prompt on \"tombs\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A Bulgar state on this river tried to convert Vladimir I of Kiev to Islam and defeated Subutai [[SOO-boo-tai]] at the Battle of Samara Bend. This river's Medieval trade route connected Northern Europe and the Sassanid Empire, and Ilya Repin [[REH-pin]] painted <em>Barge Haulers on [this river]</em> . Tatarstan and Astrakhan lie on this river, which lends its name to a city formerly known as Stalingrad. For ten points, name this longest river in Europe which flows into the Caspian Sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Volga</u></b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This island is home to Yokoi's [[YO-KOYS]] Cave, which commemorates a Japanese soldier who remained hidden on this island for 28 years after World War Two. Japanese armies were expelled from this island after a landing at Apra Harbor. This island's largest city is Dededo [[DAY-DAY-doh]], and its capital is Hag\u00e5t\u00f1a [[huh-GAHT-nyuh]]. This home of the Chamorro people is the westernmost territory of the United States. For ten points, name this Micronesian territory, the largest and southernmost of the Mariana Islands.", "answer": "<b><u>Guam</u></b> (or <b><u>Gu\u00e5han</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The namesake of this landform attacked the Royal Society for \"meddling in matters of which they know little,\" specifically regarding surveying. This landform was once called peak \"B\" by John Armstrong, a subordinate of Andrew Waugh who decided its permanent name. The namesake of this landform led the Great Trigonometric Survey to map India, and a 1922 expedition up this peak was the first to use bottled oxygen. In 1953, Edmund Hillary and the Sherpa Tenzing Norgay scaled, for ten points, what tallest mountain in the world?", "answer": "Mount <b><u>Everest</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "One author wrote during one of these events, \"I have never lived so merrily.\" One of these events, which may have been ended by a fire, was written about in the diary of Samuel Pepys [[PEEPS]]. Another of these events named for Justinian supposedly began in Pelesium and traveled by grain ship to Constantinople. A 14th century iteration of these events was likely begun by Genoese traders and killed half of Europe\u2019s population. For ten points, name these \u201cplagues\u201d caused by flea infested rats.", "answer": "Outbreaks of <b><u>Bubonic</u></b> Plague (accept <b><u>Plague</u></b> before mentioned; accept The <b><u>Black Death</u></b>; accept Great <b><u>Plague</u></b> of London before \"plague\"; accept <b><u>Plague</u></b> of Justinian before \"plague\"; prompt on \u201cPandemic\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The town of Kent, New York is home to the largest indoor statue of this figure in the West. A statue of this figure faces the Kala Wewa reservoir in the village of Avukana [[AH-vue-KAH-nah]]. The largest stone statue of this figure was built to protect sailors at the confluence of the Min and Dadu Rivers. This figure is depicted sitting in a half-lotus position in a 302-foot tall statue in Thailand. For ten points, name this ancient Indian religious figure, who was formerly depicted at Bamiyan.", "answer": "<b><u>Buddha</u></b> (accept <b><u>Siddartha</u><u>Gautama</u></b>, accept either underlined word; accept <b><u>Maitreya</u></b>; accept Great <b><u>Buddha</u></b>; accept Avukana <b><u>Buddha</u></b>; accept Leshan Giant <b><u>Buddha</u></b>)  The historical Buddha is traditionally believed to have been born in what is today this Himalayan nation.  ANSWER: Federal Democratic Republic of <b><u>Nepal</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man argued before the U.S. Supreme Court in <em>Fletcher v. Peck</em> and befriended Tsar Alexander I as the first U.S. ambassador to Russia. This man suspended the Treaty of Indian Springs after learning it had been forced upon the Muscogee and led the repeal of a gag rule preventing Congressional debates on abolition. As Secretary of State, this man helped create the Monroe Doctrine. For ten points, name this son of a former president who in 1828 lost the presidency to Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "John <b><u>Q</u></b>uincy <b><u>Adams</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's Palace of Culture and Science was in the Seven Sisters style,</u></b> <b><u>while its Smyk [[SMIKE]] Department store was in a modernist style. This country's</u></b> <b><u>anti-religious campaign included \"patriot priests,\" and this country's (+)</u> Pewex [[PEH-vex]] shops sold western items and only accepted U.S. dollars. Leaders of this country included Edward Gierek [[ED-vart GYEH-rek]] and W\u0142adys\u0142aw Gomu\u0142ka [[vwah-DIH-swahf gah-MOO-kah]]. Roundtable Talks were hosted in this country with (*) </b>Solidarity. For ten points, name this home country of Lech Wa\u0142\u0119sa [[LEK vuh-WEHN-suh]].", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Poland</u></b> (accept <b><u>Polish</u></b> People's Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The film</u> </b><em><b><u>Darwin's Nightmare</u></b></em><b><u> documents overfishing in this body of water. The</u></b> <b><u>first European to see this body of water was John Hanning Speke [[SPEAK]]. This body</u></b> <b><u>of water's sole discharge flows past Jinja [[JEEN-jah]] and through the (+)</u> Nalubaale [[NAH-loo-BAHL-eh]] Power Station. Ferries on this body of water connect cities such as Kisumu, Mwanza, and Bukoba. The explorer Henry Morton (*) </b>Stanley claimed that this lake was the source of the Nile. For ten points, name this largest lake in Africa, named for a long-reigning English queen.", "answer": "Lake <b><u>Victoria</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>As a young man, this son of a Calvinist minister was assigned to a small island</u></b> <b><u>off of Brazil by the Dutch West India Company. The Flushing Remonstrance was a</u></b> <b><u>petition to this man to allow (+)</u> Quakers to openly worship in one colony. This governor fought the short-lived Peach Tree War with Susquehannock natives after the conquest of New Sweden. This director-general surrendered to the troops of the Duke of York in 1664 and built the street that became (*) </b>Wall Street. For ten points, name this Dutchman who led the city of New Amsterdam.", "answer": "Peter (or Petrus) <b><u>Stuyvesant</u></b> [[STAI-vuh-suhnt]]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The tradition of building rectangular \"paradise\" examples of these locations</u></b> <b><u>dates back to the Achaemenid [ah-keh-MEE-nid]] Empire. While fleeing Persia,</u></b> <b><u>Baha'u'llah stayed at one of these locations in Baghdad named Ridv\u00e1n. Before the (+)</u></b> <b>crucifixion, Jesus sweat drops of blood in one of these locations named Gethsemane. The confluence of the Tigris and the Euphrates is described as the location of one of these places in the (*) </b>book of Genesis. For ten points, name this type of location, one of which named Eden was where God created the first humans.", "answer": "<b><u>Garden</u></b> (accept <b><u>Garden</u></b> of Eden; accept <b><u>Garden</u></b> of Gethsemane)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>This monument was originally proposed by Doane Robinson, who intended to</u></b> <b><u>build it on the Needles. This monument was intended to house a vault containing</u></b> <b><u>valuable U.S. documents. This monument was built on a site whose local name means</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> \"Six Grandfathers,\" and the construction of this monument led to creation of the Crazy Horse Memorial in protest. This monument was made in the (*) </b>Black Hills by the sculptor Gutzon Borglum. For ten points, name this large mountain carving located in South Dakota, which depicts four U.S. presidents.", "answer": "Mount <b><u>Rushmore</u></b> National Memorial", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Michimalonco [[mee-kee-mah-LOHN-koh]] burned this colonial city to the</u></b> <b><u>ground while founder Pedro de Valdivia was away fighting the Mapuche [[mah-POO-</u><u>chay]]. In this city\u2019s Moneda Palace, President (+)</u> Salvador Allende [[ah-YEN-day]] used a gun given to him by Fidel Castro to defend himself from right-wing insurgents. Bernardo O'Higgins declared himself supreme dictator of one South American nation in this city, and the U.S.-backed (*) </b>Augusto Pinochet captured this capital city in a 1973 coup. For ten points, name this capital of Chile.", "answer": "<b><u>Santiago</u></b> de Chile", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The first of these men, named Augustine, successfully converted King</u></b> <b><u>\u00c6thelberht of Kent, according to the Venerable Bede [[BEED]]. Misinterpreted orders</u></b> <b><u>by Henry II led to Hugh de Morville and three other (+)</u> knights killing a man in this position in his own cathedral. Another man in this position, Thomas Cranmer, affirmed the (*) </b>annulment of King Henry VIII and Catherine of Aragon, unlike the Roman Catholic pope. For ten points, name this highest position of religious authority in England, once held by Thomas \u00e0 Becket.", "answer": "<b><u>Archbishop</u></b> of <b><u>Canterbury</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This event effectively ended after Paul Revere's grandson, Joseph, performed</u></b> <b><u>a specific action at Sonoma Barracks. This event included the Klamath Lake massacre</u></b> <b><u>and was led by William B. (*)</u> Ide and \"Stuttering Zeke\" Merritt. Participants were supported by Commodore John Sloat's USS </b><em><b>Portsmouth</b></em><b> during this event which included the Battle of Olumpali. John (*) </b>C. Fr\u00e9mont encouraged this event which included the capture of Monterey by U.S. Marines. A Grizzly bear was used as the symbol of, for ten points, what California revolt?", "answer": "<b><u>Bear Flag</u></b> Revolt", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Nobu Shirase [[she-RAH-seh]] visited this location in 1910, celebrating the</u></b> <b><u>coronation of King George V along the way. Mercator Cooper made what is considered</u></b> <b><u>the first documented visit to this location. The bomb vessels</u> </b><em><b><u>Erebus</u></b></em><b><u> and</u> </b><em><b><u>Terror</u></b></em><b><u> were</u></b> <b><u>sent to this location under James Clark (*)</u> Ross. Aeneas Mackintosh visited this location but died in the </b><em><b>Nimrod</b></em><b> expedition. The Terra Nova expedition visited this location under Robert (*) </b>Falcon Scott. Roald Amundsen visited, for ten points, what continent, the location of the South Pole?", "answer": "<b><u>Antarctica</u></b> (prompt on \"South Pole\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}], "bonuses": []}